Inventory of the Jean Helen Meadowcroft papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Jean Helen Meadowcroft papers
1966-2001
85027
Hoover Institution Archives
28 manuscript boxes (11.2 linear feet)
The Jean Helen Meadowcroft collection contains significant materials relating to educational assistance programs in Bolivia, Peru, Guatemala, Lesotho, and Nepal. After serving as a Peace Corps volunteer in Bolivia in 1966-1968, Meadowcroft joined the United States Agency for International Development and worked on a number of agency programs designed to improve education in poorer countries. The bulk of the collection relates to programs in Bolivia, Lesotho, and Nepal. The collection largely consists of reports, correspondence, memoranda, and instructional materials. There are also some sound recordings and videorecordings in the collection.
Meadowcroft, Jean Helen.
Arrangement Statement
The collection is arranged into 11 series: Bolivian education file; Peruvian education file; Guatemalan education file; Printed matter; Meetings file; African education file; Nepalese education file; Radio education and distance learning file; Slides; Sound recordings; Videorecordings
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1985.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
After serving as a Peace Corps volunteer in Bolivia in 1966-1968, Meadowcroft joined the United States Agency for International Development and worked on a number of agency programs designed to improve education in poorer countries. The bulk of the collection relates to programs in Bolivia, Lesotho, and Nepal.
Meadowcroft was involved in Bolivia in efforts to implement bilingual instruction, using indigenous languages such as Quecha, in addition to Spanish, as part of the curriculum. In Lesotho, Meadowcroft participated in programs relating to primary education, and she also was active in the promotion of science education in Africa generally. In Nepal, Meadowcroft helped to run programs designed to improve literacy in the country, as well as ones specifically aimed at educating Nepalese women. During her time with U.S. AID, Meadowcroft also specialized in the field of radio education, and worked on a number of distance learning projects in various countries.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Jean Helen Meadowcroft collection contains significant materials relating to educational assistance programs in Bolivia, Peru, Guatemala, Lesotho, and Nepal. The collection largely consists of reports, correspondence, memoranda, and instructional materials. There are also some sound recordings and videorecordings in the collection.
The collection contains a considerable amount of educational materials related to the programs Meadowcroft participated in, including textbooks, teachers' guides, and handbooks. There are also a large number of reports evaluating various U.S. AID programs, as well as other reports detailing social and economic conditions in the countries where these programs were implemented. Additionally, there are sound recordings and videorecordings relating to some of the projects that Meadowcroft participated in or advised as a U.S. AID official.
United States. Agency for International Development.; Education--Bolivia.; Education--Guatemala.; Education--Lesotho.; Education--Nepal.; Education--Peru.; Educational assistance, American.; Rural development--Bolivia.
- Bolivian education file, 1966-1998
  - Reports, 1970-1980
    - 1970 (Box-folder 1: 1-2)
    - 1974 (Box-folder 1: 3-5)
    - 1975 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - 1976 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - 1977 (Box-folder 1: 8-10)
    - 1979 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - 1980 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Agency for International Development loan proposal, 1975 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Alliance for Progress loan agreements, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Ministry of Education statutes, 1978 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and reports, 1978-1981
    - 1978-1979 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - 1980-1981 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Pamphlets, 1973-1979 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Monthly project status reports, 1977-1980
    - 1977-1978 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - 1979 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - 1980 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Clippings, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Summer Institute of Linguistics correspondence and reports, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Bilingual Education Project records, 1975-1983
    - Correspondence, 1979-1983 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Reports, 1975-1982
      - 1975 (Box-folder 3: 3)
      - 1977 (Box-folder 3: 4)
      - 1978 (Box-folder 3: 5)
      - 1979 (Box-folder 3: 6-7)
      - 1980 (Box-folder 3: 8-10)
      - 1980 (Box-folder 4: 1-4)
  - Textbooks, 1973-1982
    - 1973 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - 1974 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - 1978 (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - 1979 (Box-folder 5: 4-9)
    - 1981 (Box-folder 5: 10-11)
    - 1982 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Nonformal education manual, 1981 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Vocabulary usage studies, 1978 (Box-folder 6: 1-2)
  - Teachers' manuals and textbooks, 1979 (Box-folder 6: 3-5)
  - Frontlines, serial issue, 1979 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Rural Education Project records, 1975-1984
    - Journal articles, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 6: 7)
    - Reports, 1978-1983
      - 1978 (Box-folder 6: 8)
      - 1979 (Box-folder 6: 9-10)
      - 1982 (Box-folder 6: 11)
      - 1983 (Box-folder 6: 12-13)
    - Statistics, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 6: 14)
    - Reports, 1980-1984
      - 1980 (Box-folder 7: 1-2)
      - 1981 (Box-folder 7: 3)
      - 1982 (Box-folder 7: 4)
      - 1982-1983 (Box-folder 7: 5)
      - 1983 (Box-folder 7: 6-7)
      - 1984 (Box-folder 7: 8-11)
    - Plans and proposals, 1979-1981
      - 1975 (Box-folder 8: 1)
      - 1977 (Box-folder 8: 2)
      - 1979 (Box-folder 8: 3)
      - 1981-1982 (Box-folder 8: 4)
      - 1982 (Box-folder 8: 5)
    - Agreements, 1977 (Box-folder 8: 6)
    - Conference proceedings, 1978-1979
      - 1978 (Box-folder 8: 7)
      - 1979 (Box-folder 8: 8)
    - Diagnostic survey of teacher training colleges, 1979 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1998
    - General, 1979-1984
      - 1979-1982 (Box-folder 9: 2)
      - 1982-1984 (Box-folder 9: 3)
    - Kavanaugh, Teresa L., 1998 (Box-folder 9: 4)
  - Proposal, 1994 (Box-folder 9: 5)
  - Plans, 1997 (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - Reports, 1981-1996
    - 1981 (Box-folder 9: 7)
    - 1996 (Box-folder 9: 8-9)
  - Printed matter, 1966-1982
    - Monographs, 1970-1979
      - 1970 (Box-folder 10: 1-3)
      - 1973 (Box-folder 10: 4-5)
      - 1974 (Box-folder 10: 6-7)
      - 1975 (Box-folder 10: 8)
      - 1976 (Box-folder 10: 9-10)
      - 1979 (Box-folder 10: 11-12)
    - Pamphlets, 1966-1981
      - 1966 (Box-folder 10: 13)
      - 1967 (Box-folder 10: 14)
      - 1970 (Box-folder 10: 15)
      - 1976 (Box-folder 10: 16)
      - 1981 (Box-folder 10: 17)
    - Serial issues, 1973-1979
      - 1970 (Box-folder 10: 18)
      - 1971 (Box-folder 10: 19)
      - 1973 (Box-folder 10: 20)
      - 1974 (Box-folder 10: 21)
      - 1975 (Box-folder 11: 1)
      - 1976 (Box-folder 11: 2)
      - 1977 (Box-folder 11: 3-6)
      - 1978 (Box-folder 11: 7)
      - 1979 (Box-folder 11: 8-13)
    - Statistical reports, 1981-1982
      - 1981 (Box-folder 11: 14)
      - 1982 (Box-folder 11: 15)
- Peruvian education file, 1978-1980
  - Plans, 1980 (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - Reports, 1978 (Box-folder 12: 2-3)
- Guatemalan education file, 1975-1997
  - Clippings, 1983 (Box-folder 12: 4)
  - Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 12: 5)
  - Reports, 1975-1983
    - 1975 (Box-folder 12: 6)
    - 1983 (Box-folder 12: 7-9)
    - 1984 (Box-folder 12: 10)
    - 1993 (Box-folder 12: 11)
    - 1997 (Box-folder 12: 12)
- Printed matter, 1983-2001
  - Program to Promote Educational Reform in Latin America and the Caribbean (PREAL), 1996-2001
    - Newsletters, 2000-2001 (Box-folder 13: 1)
    - Papers and reports, 1996-2001
      - 1996 (Box-folder 13: 2)
      - 1997 (Box-folder 13: 3-5)
      - 1998 (Box-folder 13: 6)
      - 1999 (Box-folder 13: 7)
      - 2000 (Box-folder 13: 8)
      - 2001 (Box-folder 13: 9)
    - Seminar proceedings, 1996 (Box-folder 13: 10)
  - United States Agency for International Development, 1983-1997
    - Pamphlet, 1990 (Box-folder 13: 11)
    - Papers, 1983-1996
      - 1983 (Box-folder 13: 12)
      - 1993 (Box-folder 13: 13-14)
      - 1995 (Box-folder 13: 15)
      - 1996 (Box-folder 13: 16)
    - Reports, 1984-1997
      - 1984 (Box-folder 14: 1)
      - 1992 (Box-folder 14: 2-3)
      - 1996 (Box-folder 14: 4)
      - 1997 (Box-folder 14: 5)
- Meetings file, 1997-1998
  - Brazil meetings on education, 1997
    - Memoranda, 1997 (Box-folder 14: 6)
    - Report, 1997 (Box-folder 14: 7)
  - Review of basic education programs, United States Agency for International Development Bureau for Latin America and the Caribbean, 1998
    - Memoranda, 1998 (Box-folder 14: 8)
    - Report, 1998 (Box-folder 14: 9)
  - Summit of the Americas, 1997-1998
    - Memoranda, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 14: 10)
    - Plans, 1997-1998
      - 1997 (Box-folder 14: 11-12)
      - 1998 (Box-folder 14: 13)
    - Press releases, 1998 (Box-folder 14: 14)
    - Report, 1998 (Box-folder 14: 15)
- African education file, 1968-1998
  - General, 1980-1998
    - Papers, 1997-1998
      - 1997 (Box-folder 15: 1)
      - 1998 (Box-folder 15: 2)
    - Report, 1980 (Box-folder 15: 3)
  - Lesotho primary education program, 1982-1996
    - Cables and memoranda, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 15: 4)
    - Program assistance approval document, 1991 (Box-folder 15: 5)
    - Reports, 1982-1996
      - 1982 (Box-folder 15: 6)
      - 1990 (Box-folder 16: 1)
      - 1991 (Box-folder 16: 2-4)
      - 1992 (Box-folder 16: 5)
      - 1994 (Box-folder 16: 6)
      - 1996 (Box-folder 16: 7)
    - Textbook, 1990 (Box-folder 16: 8)
  - Science education programs, 1968-1983
    - Memorandum, 1982 (Box-folder 16: 9)
    - Reports, 1970-1983
      - 1970 (Box-folder 16: 10)
      - 1971 (Box-folder 16: 11)
      - 1973 (Box-folder 16: 12)
      - 1980 (Box-folder 16: 13)
      - 1980 (Box-folder 17: 1)
      - 1983 (Box-folder 17: 2-3)
    - Teachers' guides, 1968-1978
      - 1968 (Box-folder 17: 4)
      - 1970 (Box-folder 17: 5-6)
      - 1971 (Box-folder 17: 7)
      - 1978 (Box-folder 17: 8)
- Nepalese education file, 1983-1995
  - Development Training Project records, 1985-1988
    - Agreement, 1985 (Box-folder 18: 1)
    - Correspondence, 1988 (Box-folder 18: 2)
    - Report, 1985 (Box-folder 18: 3)
  - Health Education and Adult Literacy Program records, 1992-1993
    - Proposal, 1992 (Box-folder 18: 4)
    - Reports, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 18: 5)
  - Literacy Expansion Project records, 1984-1983
    - Correspondence, 1989-1993 (Box-folder 18: 6)
    - Project identification document, 1989 (Box-folder 18: 7)
    - Proposals, 1990 (Box-folder 18: 8)
    - Reports, 1984-1993
      - 1984 (Box-folder 18: 9)
      - 1987 (Box-folder 18: 10)
      - 1988 (Box-folder 18: 11-12)
      - 1989 (Box-folder 18: 13)
      - 1990-1993 (Box-folder 18: 14)
  - Radio Education Teacher Training Project records, 1984-1990
    - Correspondence, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 18: 15)
    - Proposal, 1984 (Box-folder 18: 16)
    - Reports, 1986-1990
      - 1986 (Box-folder 19: 1)
      - 1988 (Box-folder 19: 2-3)
      - 1989 (Box-folder 19: 4-7)
      - 1990 (Box-folder 19: 8)
  - Women in Development Program, 1988-1990
    - Plan, 1988 (Box-folder 19: 9)
    - Report, 1990 (Box-folder 19: 10)
  - Other materials relating to education and social conditions in Nepal, 1980-1997
    - Monograph on U.S. assistance to Nepal, 1991 (Box-folder 19: 11)
    - Reports, 1981-1997
      - General, 1981-1990 (Box-folder 20: 1)
      - Education, 1981-1993
        - 1981 (Box-folder 20: 2)
        - 1988 (Box-folder 20: 3-4)
        - 1993 (Box-folder 20: 5)
      - Status of women, 1980-1997
        - 1980 (Box-folder 20: 6)
        - 1981 (Box-folder 21: 1-7)
        - 1996 (Box-folder 22: 1)
        - 1997 (Box-folder 22: 2)
    - Teachers' guide, 1986 (Box-folder 22: 3)
    - Textbooks, 1985-1988
      - 1985 (Box-folder 22: 5)
      - 1986 (Box-folder 22: 6-7)
      - 1987 (Box-folder 22: 8-9)
      - 1988 (Box-folder 22: 10-15)
- Radio education and distance learning file, 1976-1991
  - Correspondence and memoranda, 1984-1991
    - 1984 (Box-folder 23: 1)
    - 1984-1985 (Box-folder 23: 2)
    - 1990-1991 (Box-folder 23: 3)
  - Conference notebook, 1990 (Box-folder 23: 4)
  - Instruction handbook, 1988 (Box-folder 23: 5)
  - Monographs, 1976-1990
    - 1976 (Box-folder 23: 6)
    - 1978 (Box-folder 23: 7)
    - 1986 (Box-folder 24: 1)
    - 1990 (Box-folder 24: 2)
  - Newsletters, 1982-1991
    - Miscellaneous, 1988-1991 (Box-folder 24: 3)
    - Development Communication Report, 1982-1990
      - 1982-1983 (Box-folder 24: 4)
      - 1984-1985 (Box-folder 24: 5)
      - 1986-1987 (Box-folder 24: 6)
      - 1988-1989 (Box-folder 24: 7)
      - 1990 (Box-folder 24: 8)
  - Reports, 1977-1995
    - General, 1977-1995
      - 1977 (Box-folder 24: 9-10)
      - 1981-1983 (Box-folder 25: 1)
      - 1984 (Box-folder 25: 2)
      - 1987 (Box-folder 25: 3)
      - 1989 (Box-folder 25: 4)
      - 1990 (Box-folder 25: 5)
      - 1994 (Box-folder 25: 6)
      - 1995 (Box-folder 25: 7)
    - Radio-Assisted Community Basic Education Project, 1984-1991
      - 1980 (Box-folder 25: 8)
      - 1984 (Box-folder 25: 9-12)
      - 1988 (Box-folder 25: 13)
      - 1991 (Box-folder 25: 14)
    - Radio Correspondence Education Project (Kenya), 1982 (Box-folder 26: 1)
    - Radio Language Arts Project (Kenya), 1981-1986
      - 1981 (Box-folder 26: 2)
      - 1983 (Box-folder 26: 3)
      - 1985 (Box-folder 26: 4)
      - 1986 (Box-folder 26: 5)
    - Radio Learning Project, 1988-1989
      - 1988 (Box-folder 26: 6)
      - 1989 (Box-folder 26: 7)
    - Radio Mathematics Project, 1980-1981
      - 1980 (Box-folder 26: 8)
      - 1981 (Box-folder 26: 9-11)
    - Radio Science Project, 1990 (Box-folder 26: 12)
- Slides, 1982-1984
  - Twenty-two 35mm slides depicting rural education projects in the Dominican Republic, 1982 (Box-folder 27: 1)
  - Eight 35mm slides depicting classroom scenes in Kenya, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 27: 2)
- Sound recordings, 1975-1989
  - One compact cassette relating to primary education in Honduras, 1975 (Box-folder 27: 3)
  - Six compact cassettes relating to the Radio Mathematics Project and other educational programs in Nicaragua, 1976 (Box-folder 27: 4-10)
  - Two compact cassettes relating to the Radio Language Arts Program in Kenya, 1985 (Box-folder 27: 11-12)
  - Two compact cassettes relating to mathematics instruction in Bolivia, 1987 (Box-folder 27: 13-14)
  - One compact cassette relating to the Radio Education Teacher Training Project in Nepal, 1988 (Box-folder 27: 15)
  - Two compact cassettes relating to the Radio Science Project in Papua New Guinea, 1989 (Box-folder 27: 16-17)
- Videorecordings, 1970-1989
  - One Betamax videocassette relating to bilingual education in Bolivia, 1970 (Box-folder 27: 18)
  - Three U-matic videocassettes relating to educational programs in Bolivia, 1980 (Box-folder 28: 1-3)
  - One VHS (PAL) videocassette relating to educational programs in Kenya and the Dominican Republic, 1982 (Box-folder 28: 4)
  - One VHS videocassette relating to the Radio Science Project in Papua New Guinea, 1988 (Box-folder 28: 5)
  - One VHS videocassette relating to the Radio Education Teacher Training Project in Nepal, 1989 (Box-folder 28: 6)